Guide to the Russell Sturgis, Jr., Family Papers
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
Russell Sturgis, Jr., papers
1808-1940
MS 2046
Yale University. Department of Manuscripts and Archives
3.67
6 boxes
The papers primarily document the personal and family life of Russell Sturgis, Jr., and include little documentation of his professional career as an architect except for clippings of articles, reviews, and obituaries contained in a scrapbook. The bulk of the collection consists of family correspondence, including letters, dated 1863-1864, written by Sturgis' brother, Appleton, while serving in the Union army, and early writings from Sturgis' college years. There are also sketchbooks of landscape and architectural drawings from European trips taken by Sturgis, dated 1858-1883, as well as a small number of family photographs.
Sturgis, Russell, 1836-1909
Painter, Thomas, 1760-1847
Scope and Contents
The papers primarily document the personal and family life of Russell Sturgis, Jr., and include little documentation of his professional career as an architect except for clippings of articles, reviews, and obituaries contained in a scrapbook. The bulk of the collection consists of family correspondence, including letters, dated 1863-1864, written by Sturgis' brother, Appleton, while serving in the Union army, and early writings from Sturgis' college years. There are also sketchbooks of landscape and architectural drawings from European trips taken by Sturgis, dated 1858-1883, as well as a small number of family photographs.
Immediate Source of Acquisition
Gift of Alexander Finley and Beatrice Sturgis Bartlett, 2016.
Biographical / Historical
Russell Sturgis, Jr. (1836-1909), the son of Russell (1804-1873) and Margaret Dawes Appleton Sturgis, was born in Chantilly, Baltimore County, Delaware. He was the oldest of four children, with two brothers, Appleton and Edward, and a sister, Kate. The family's primary residence was in New York City, where Russell, Jr., graduated from the Free Academy of New York (now the City College of New York) in 1856. He studied architecture under Leopold Eidlitz and then, in 1858, travelled to Europe, where he spent some time studying in Munich. After returning to America in 1862, he married Sarah Maria Barney, daughter of Danford N. Barney, in 1864. They had seven children: Margaret (Mrs. Hector W. Thomas), Danford N. B. (a twin brother of Danford died at birth), Beatrice Cynthia Barney (Mrs. Philip Golden Bartlett), Sarah B., and twins Lyman B. (Van) and Edward B. Sturgis was an architect who designed buildings across the eastern part of the country, with the majority in New York state and Connecticut. These included four buildings at Yale: Farnham Hall (1868), Durfee Hall (1870), Battell Chapel (1872-73), and Lawrance Hall (1884). While not unsuccessful as an architect, he was more well-known as a commentator on architecture and art. He was a prolific author of articles published in the popular press and in professional journals. In addition to editing Dictionary of Architecture and Building and a revision of Wilhelm Lübke's Outline of the History of Art, he was the author of several volumes, including European Architecture: A Historical Study, How to Judge Architecture, and A History of Architecture. He was active in many professional and artistic organizations, including the American Institute of Architects and the Metropolitan Museum of Art. He received an honorary degree from Yale in 1872 and served as the Chair of Architecture and the Arts of Design at City College from 1878-to 1880, when ill health led him to retire from his professorship and to curtail his architectural practice. He continued write and lecture on art and architecture until shortly before his death on February 11, 1909 in New York City.
Arrangement
The materials are arranged according to document type.
Conditions Governing Access
The materials are open for research.
Architecture -- Notebooks, sketchbooks, etc.; United States -- History -- Civil War, 1861-1865; Sturgis, Russell, 1836-1909; Sturges family
- General
  - Biographical notes by Mrs. Russell Sturgis, After 1860 (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Citations (photocopies), 1891-1896 (Box 6, Folder 2)
  - Diaries
    - Margaret Sturgis Thomas reference diary, 1897-1911 (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Russell Sturgis, 1852-1855 (Box 1, Folder 3)
  - Notebook, 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 4)
    Scope and Contents
    Russell Sturgis recorded synopses of letters sent during his European travels. There are also loose pages of notes from his time in Italy.
  - Notes on vocal lessons and a copy of Clionian Society of New York Free Academy constitution, Circa 1851 (Box 1, Folder 5)
  - Obituary notices for Sturgis, 1909 February (Box 1, Folder 6)
  - Passport, 1859-1860 (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Photographs
    - Family, Circa 1850-mid 20th century (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Sarah M. Barney Sturgis, age 21, Circa 1858 (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Triptych of family portraits, Circa 1850-circa 1880 (Box 5)
  - Scrapbook, 1897-1910 (Box 6, Folder 1)
  - Sketchbooks
    - Compiled sketches of architectural detail and decorative items, 1859-1895 (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - French village life and landscapes, 1883 (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Italian architectural detail, 1860 (Box 1, Folder 12)
- Correspondence, 1808-1907
  - General, 1808-1907, undated (Box 2, Folder 1-17)
    Much of this correspondence details family life of the Sturgis children. There are also letters from Appleton Sturgis describing his service in the Union Army, 1863-1864.
  - A., E. D., 1851-1852 (Box 3, Folder 1)
  - Cuyler, M. M., 1860-1861 (Box 3, Folder 2)
  - From children, 1873-1874 (Box 3, Folder 3)
  - To children while living abroad, 1883, 1887 (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - From family while travelling east from Montpelier, 1881 February-March (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Sturgis, Catherine, 1856-1862 (Box 3, Folder 6)
- Writings, 1848-1867
  Arrangement
  These documents are arranged in chronological order.
  - Compositions written at N. Thayer's school, 1848-1851 (Box 4, Folder 1)
  - Essays, New York Free Academy, class DC (freshman), 1852-1853 (Box 4, Folder 2)
  - "Macauley As a Poet," for the Clionian Society, 1854 March 17 (Box 4, Folder 3)
  - "The Loss of the Arctic," for the Clionian Society, 1854 October 20 (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Article contributed to Clionian Magazine, 1854-1855 (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Essays, New York Free Academy, junior class, 1854-1855 (Box 4, Folder 6)
  - "The Russian War," poem for Clionian Magazine, 1854-1855 (Box 4, Folder 7)
  - "The People's Art," speech delivered at New York Free Academy Junior Exhibition, 1855 February 16 (Box 4, Folder 8)
  - Commencement oration (various versions), 1856 July 22 (Box 4, Folder 9)
  - Poems and fragments, 1856, undated (Box 4, Folder 10)
  - Untitled, 1865-1867, undated (Box 4, Folder 11)
  - Early attempts at fiction, Undated (Box 4, Folder 12)
- Painter Family, 1900
  The original documents were written by Thomas Painter in 1836. Included in the biographical material is information on Thomas Painter's service during the Revolutionary War, first in the militia and later in the navy. There is also significant information on his maritime career before and after the war. The versions in this collection are manuscript copies made by his granddaughter, Alice Bartlett, in 1900. There are also some loose pages of genealogical information concerning the Painter family. The material became part of the Sturgis family records through Philip Golden Bartlett, brother of Alice Bartlett and husband of Russell Sturgis' daughter Beatrice.
  - "History of the Painter Family in the Parish of West Haven, and Also of the Parish Itself Up to the Year 1836" (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - "History of the Life and Family of Thomas Painter" (Box 4, Folder 13)